Hey guys, I'm back with Skellyy here.
Uh, this video is going to be on glute
squeeze and pelvic uh, torque in in like
squatting and deadlifting and hip
thrusting movements.
So, I guess it's also on the lumbo
pelvic hip complex biomechanics. So if
you look here at skelly, this is the
lumbar spine. This here is the pelvis.
This is the SI joint. And this is these
are the hips. So this all works
together. This whole region kind of
functions uh and coordinates together
and there's a an optimal manner in which
it coordinates during movement to
produce the best results. So,
um, if if you're in the bottom of a
squat,
you don't want to go into you don't want
a butt wing. You don't want to go this
way. You don't want the pelvis to rotate
this way. You don't want the lumbar
spine to flatten out. And so, you in
order to keep this nice stable position
here like this, the erectors have to
fire very hard to hold that anterior
pelvic tilt.
So it's creating there might not be any
pelvic motion as you come down.
You might not have a lot of motion there
but the torque is created the rotational
force to hold that in place. So you will
the erectors will help the the hip
flexors do it too but in the squat it's
mainly the erectors creating the
anterior pelvic tilt torque. Now
the top of a squat is pretty unloaded.
It's not very hard. So, you don't have
to like squeeze the glutes hard to lock
out a squat because the top half is so
easy. But in a deadlift, when you get to
the top of a deadlift,
you will see that you want you don't
want to achieve a lock out by just
bending the back this way and
hyperextending the lumbar spine. You
want to achieve a lock out as you come
up like this. You want a strong glute
squeeze
to push the hips forward. Rather than
thinking of the lumbar spine twerking
backwards, think of the glutes pushing
the hips forward. Now, here's what I
want to show you.
See if you can zoom in on my glute
region. If I squeeze the glutes as hard
as I can from a from a standing
position, just like this,
you will notice my pelvis posterior
tilts a little bit. And I also
if if I'm standing like this, my feet if
I squeeze my glutes really hard, I will
notice that my feet start to turn out a
little bit. What this means is just
squeezing my glutes creates hip hip
external rotation torque and posterior
pelvic tilt torque because if you can
see from here, you know, I'm in neutral
and then I squeeze my glutes and it
tucks under a little bit. Now, when you
lock out a deadlift, you just want to
squeeze the glutes. So, here's my lumbar
spine. If I squeeze the glutes hard, my
lumbar spine is not affected.
So this is when I when we talk about an
American deadlift where you're squeezing
the glutes, my lumbar spine does not
move out of position. You never come up
like this and then go and move your and
flex your lumbar spine. So it's very
important to understand that. The same
thing applies for catal swings.
When you're in the bottom of a kettle
bell swing or let's talk about a
deadlift. When I'm in the bottom of a
deadlift,
okay, I want, you know, it's like our
natural tendency to be rounded over. But
when I create a nice stable arch, what
am I doing? I do this and create an
arch. Okay? I am using the erectors to
get the spine in neutral and to keep the
pelvis to stabilize the pelvis. So, I'm
stabilizing both the lumbar spine and
the pelvis. those work together. They're
connected. And so right here, I'm
creating anterior pelvic tilt torque.
But then as I come up
right here, about right here is when I
switch. Now I want the glute squeeze.
Glute squeeze there. So if you see my
glutes are on right now.
A lot of people, you will see them at
the top of a deadlift or a kettle bell
swing and their glutes aren't turned on.
They're just kind of using their
erectors and hamstrings and things like
that and they shut their glutes off. You
want to practice squeezing the glutes
hard to lock it out because that
actually protects the lumbar spine. So
again if we look at scale here
if
from right here
coming up instead of the lumbar spine
head we're extending rearward the glutes
push forward like this and there's going
to be some slight posterior pelvic tilt
torque right here just like that with
the glute squeeze but it's this very
stable position because you're squeezing
the glutes. The lumbar spine is not
tough. You don't lose that lumbar spine
position. It's just a glute squeeze.
You're not thinking lumbar spine at all.
You're just thinking of a strong glute
glute contraction. And this glute
contraction is what keeps everything
stable. So
I did a little
experiment where I had around 10 strong
lifters, power lifters, and really
strong guys. And I told him to do this.
As I said, first I want you to not
squeeze your glutes at all. And I want
you to bend backwards as far as you can
and really focus on hyperextending the
lumbar spine. And I had them do that and
they get to here and every one of them
would say, "Oh, that hurts. You know, I
get pain." And then I said, "Okay, now
squeeze your glutes and go back.
keep your glutes squeezed in bend back.
And most of them reported to me that
they didn't have they didn't feel any
pain when their glutes were squeezed. So
squeezing the glutes helps protect the
spine.
It helps protect the spine when you
round. It helps protect the spine when
you hyper extend. But it's kind of this
the glue that holds everything together.
So when I squeeze the glutes again, you
get this nice stable
stable contraction where it's twisting
outwards on the hips and tucking the
pelvis under. So you're not going to
lose that. It's a very stable hip
position. So, make sure that when you
lock out a deadlift and at the top of a
kettle bell swing. So, when I do a
kettle bell swing and I'm at the top,
when you see this,
when when the bell is floating up, my
glutes are turned on. When the bell
floats up and then the bell starts
coming down, I wait till about here till
I release them and go back down. So hold
that glute contraction. And that's
important because
when the bell floats outwards, there's
this period if the glutes aren't turned
on where the bell pulls away from you.
And this creates some shearing force on
the lumbar spine. Meaning
the bell is swinging out this way. Okay?
So you got the kettle bell swinging out
this way.
And if the glutes aren't turned on,
this pulls this way on the spine.
you get this shearing force, splitting
apart force, but if the glutes are
turned on, it's going to help stabilize
this area too. So that's why it's
important. So again, this also applies
to a hip thrust.
When you are So come back around this
way. When you do a hip thrust
at the very top,
you if if you're going to have a lot of
sheer force if you are if your spine is
hyperextended.
But if you keep the torso flat like this
and then just push the glutes upwards
and this torso remains flat, you're
going to greatly reduce the stress on
the low back. So just from here
come up like that. So from here see that
as opposed to this hyper extended
where I'm going to have more sheer force
because my glutes aren't going to be
turned on as well. So make sure that
when you come up to the top of a hip
thrust, you're pushing the hips upwards
with the glutes. Okay? And make sure
there's a strong glute contraction at
the very top of the movement. So,
you want to recap
at the top of a deadlift, the top of a
catal swing, and the top of the hip
thrust, you want a strong glute
contraction characterized by
posterior pelvic tilt torque, hip
extension torque, and hip external
rotation torque. Now, you don't want any
lumbar spine motion, though. So it's
just a glute squeeze without affecting
the lumbar spine. So if you have to
practice and make sure you know like we
do the American deadlift where you come
down to here and squeeze the glutes. My
lumbar spine does not change position
here. I'm just squeezing the glutes.
It's not movement at the lumbar spine.
And one last thing I want to show you
is that
posterior pelvic tilt and hip extension
are basically very similar. They mimic
each other. So as come up into hip
extension,
I'm right here. I'm not quite at
terminal hip extension. If I squeeze the
glutes to go into hip extension, what
happens? The hip extends. So this is
here's the head of the femur inside the
acetabulum. If I squeeze the glutes, the
hip extends.
But if the femur stays fixed and I
squeeze the glutes and this doesn't
move, you will post your pelvic tilt,
which does this,
which the pelvis tucks under like that.
It's the same thing. They both kind of
create hip hyper extension. So here
might be like where hip extension
reaches neutral. You get that extra
glute squeeze.
If it's hip hyperextension, the femur
moves rearward. If it's posterior pelvic
tilt, the femur stays put and the pelvis
tilts upon the femur, but they both
create that twisting torque in there to
keep everything stable.
And you also create it creates a strong
glute because the glute fibers run this
way. it will twist outwards like this.
So you'll get this twisting out external
rotation force as well which kind of
just squeezing the glutes kind of screws
your feet into place. So you don't have
to think of screwing your feet in the
ground. You just think of the glute
squeeze and it takes care of it for you.
But it's a very stable contraction. So
anyway, I hope you like the video on
Lombo pelvic hip complex biomechanics.
Thank you very much for watching.